Finding Aid for William B. Mershon Papers, 1848-1943
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William B. Mershon Papers
1848-1943
Mershon, William B., 1856-1943
851844 Aa 2
Saginaw, Michigan, lumberman and businessman, and Michigan State Tax Commissioner, 1912 and wildlife conservationist and sportsman. Papers include extensive correspondence files, business records and photographs.
46.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
14 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of William B. Mershon and family (donor no. 51 ) and came to the library in 1944
The collection is open for research.
William Butts Mershon was the third generation of his family to engage in lumbering in and around Saginaw, Michigan. When he first became active in the family business in 1866 the firm was already large and diversified. In addition to lumbering and the operation of a planing mill, the firm was one of the nation's largest manufacturers of knock-down wooden boxes, the standard form of storage and shipping box prior to the development of cardboard cartons.
After spending several years working within the family concern, Mershon founded his own company, William B. Mershon and Company. He also formed several other partnerships including one formed by himself, S.L. Eastman, William Schuette, and Parker, Sheldon & Co. While he divided his time among many interests, after 1905 he generally concentrated on William B. Mershon and Co., rather than his other business interests. This firm manufactured bandsaws designed by his brother Edward. In 1926 William Mershon sold the business and retired.
Mershon also had financial interests outside the state of Michigan. In 1900 he became a stockholder (later he was elected president) of the Saginaw & Manistee Lumber Company, headquartered at Williams, Arizona. He also invested in copper mining in Arizona and lumbering operations in Montana.
Privately, Mershon was a well known conservationist and sportsman. He published two volumes, one regarding the passenger pigeon and the other relating his hunting and fishing experiences over fifty years. He also was active in Saginaw political life, serving as mayor of Saginaw (1894-1895), city alderman, member of both the parks and the cemetery commissions, and the citizen's water committee.
The Mershon Papers are arranged in two distinct subgroups, the Paper Records and the Microfilmed Records. The paper records are primarily personal, but contain some business records while the microfilmed material is primarily business records. Each of the subgroups is further divided into series.
Paper Records subgroup Papers - Chronological Papers - Undated Letterbooks Saginaw and Manistee Lumber Company Hunting and Fishing Business Papers Photographs
Microfilmed Records subgroup William B. Mershon & Company Mershon, Schuette and Parker Atlas Oil Corporation Saginaw and Manistee Lumber Co. Personal Journals
The William Mershon collection consists of correspondence dealing with Mershon's various activities as a lumberman, Saginaw businessman, and member of the State Tax Commission in 1912. Subjects included in the papers are Michigan wildlife conservation, the Michigan Sportsmen Association, the Michigan Manufacturers Association, the Michigan State Tax Commission, Michigan politics, the Democratic party, personal business investments, lumbering and mining interest, and personal affairs.
The collection also includes diaries, a book of notes on hunting and fishing trips, and various business records such as cash books, time books, ledgers, and journals. These primarily concern his investments and lumbering business. Many of the business records are available on microfilm. The collection also includes photographs.
Subjects:
Account books.; Diaries.; Business records.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1936.; Fishing--Michigan.; Forests and forestry--Michigan.; Hunting--Michigan.; Huron National Forest (Mich.); Logging--Michigan.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Manufactures--Michigan.; Mershon, Wm. B. (William Butts), 1856-1943.; Michigan. Dept. of Conservation.; Michigan Forestry Association.; Michigan. Forestry Commission.; Michigan Manufacturer's Association.; Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Michigan Sportsmen's Association.; Michigan. State Tax Commission.; Michigan Wildlife Conservation Association.; Mines and mineral resources--Michigan.; Saginaw (Mich.); Strikes and lockouts--Michigan.; Taxation--Michigan.; United States. Congress.; United States. Supreme Court.
Contributors:
Ashurst, Henry Fountain, 1874-1962; Avery, Waldo A.; Baker, William F.; Bland, Joseph Edward, 1866-; Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Campbell, Thomas E., b. 1858.; Carton, Augustus C.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957.; Doremus, Frank Ellsworth, 1865-1947.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Fordney, Joseph W. (Joseph Warren), 1853-1932.; Garfield, Charles William, 1848-1934.; Glaspie, Andrew Bird, 1876-; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938.; Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Alexander Joseph), 1873-1953.; Hamilton, Edward LaRue, 1857-1923.; Harrison, Francis Burton, 1873-1957.; Hart, Michael James, 1877-1951.; Hawes, Harry B.; Hough, Emerson, 1857-1923.; Humphrey, George M. (George Magoffin), b. 1890.; Humphrey, Watts S.; Hunsaker, Walter Jerome, 1857-1939.; Kelley, Patrick Henry, 1867-1925.; King, Francis, Mrs., 1863-1948; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Kracher, Horatio S.; Linsley, Edward B., b. 1847.; Macauley, Thomas Babbington.; Mapes, Carl Edgar, 1874-1939.; Maxey, John O., 1871-1920.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1939.; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Morley, George Bidwell, 1857-1935.; Munger, Edith Cushway, 1865-1945.; New, Harry S. (Harry Stewart), 1858-1937.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Pearson, William J., 1860-; Penney, Harvey A., 1866-; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Rayburn, Robert H., 1866-; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roth, Filibert, 1858-1925.; Saginaw and Manistee Lumber Company.; Shields, Robert Hazen, 1905-; Sleeper, Albert E., 1862-1934.; Smith, Hal Horace, 1903-; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Smoot, Reed, 1862-1941.; Sterling, Louis T.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Tuttle, Arthur J., 1868-1944.; Underwood, Oscar Wilder, 1862-1929.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Vincent, Bird J., 1880-1931; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; Watkins, Lucius Whitney, 1873-; Whitney, Joseph H., b. 1858.; Williams, John Sharp, 1854-1932.; Wood, Edwin O., b. 1840.; Young, Horace Olin, 1850-1917.
Visual Terms - Subjects:
Bliss Park (Saginaw, Mich.); Boats.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Saginaw.; Camping.; Fish.; Fishing.; Grayling fishing.; Hunting.; Laborers.; Lumber industry.; Lumberman's Memorial (Iosco County, Mich.); Mershon, Wm. B. (William Butts), 1856-1943.; Mershon family.; Mining.; Monuments and memorials.; Photographs.; Railroads--Michigan.; Rochester Salt and Lumber Company (Saginaw, Mich.); Saginaw (Mich.); Saginaw (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Travel.; World War, 1914-1918.
Genre/Form:
Account books.; Diaries.; Photographs.
- Paper records
  - Papers - Chronological
    - 1848-May 1904 (Box 1)
    - June 1904-January 1907 (Box 2)
    - February 1907-July 1908 (Box 3)
    - August 1908-September 1909 (Box 4)
    - October 1909-November 1910 (Box 5)
    - December 1910-November 1911 (Box 6)
    - December 1911-October 1912 (Box 7)
    - November 1912-December 1913 (Box 8)
    - January 1914-August 1914 (Box 9)
    - September 1914-October 1915 (Box 10)
    - November 1915-October 1916 (Box 11)
    - November 1916-December 1917 (Box 12)
    - January 1918-September 1918 (Box 13)
    - October 1918-August 1919 (Box 14)
    - September 1919-July 1920 (Box 15)
    - August 1920-May 1921 (Box 16)
    - June 1921-December 1922 (Box 17)
    - January 1923-June 1924 (Box 18)
    - July 1924-March 1926 (Box 19)
    - April 1926-February 1928 (Box 20)
    - March 1928-February 1930 (Box 21)
    - March 1930-September 1932 (Box 22)
    - October 1932-September 1936 (Box 23)
    - October 1936-May 1939 (Box 24)
    - June 1939-December 1941 (Box 25)
    - January 1942-December 1943 (Box 26)
    - Income tax materials, 1918-1942 (Box 26)
    - Wildlife conservation materials, 1915-1917 (Box 26)
    - Autobiographical and genealogical materials (Box 26)
  - Papers, undated
    - California Pine Box & Lumber Co., Articles of Incorporation, By-laws, Shook Sales Agreement, Shook Contract, Lumber Contract (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Rates on Lumber Cases in Arizona (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Benefit Plan for Employees of Calumet & Arizona Mining Company (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Articles of Incorporation and By-laws of American-Saginaw Development Company (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Indebtedness of George A. Beach to W.B. Mershon (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Undated correspondence (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Michigan Manufacturers Association (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Michigan Board of State Tax Commissioners (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Sale to W.B. Baker Contract (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Labor Negotiations (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Undated Business correspondence and records (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Personal correspondence, undated (Box 27, Folder 4-7)
    - Mortgages, Insurance Policies, Last Will and Testament, Trust Agreements, Stock letters (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence on construction of Holly Hunting House in Mississippi and Saginaw-American Development Company reports (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Saginaw & Manistee Lumber Company records (Box 27, Folder 10-11)
    - Saginaw American Development Corporation records (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Materials on fish habits, etc. (Box 27, Folder 12-13)
    - Correspondence and Printed materials William Jennings Bryan Claim (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Imprints of W.B. Mershon's Stamps (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Manuscript of "Recollections of My Fifty Years" (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Original materials on "Recollections of My Fifty Years Hunting and Fishing" (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Duplicate manuscript of Recollections book (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - Letterbooks
    - November 4, 1901-September 30, 1902 (Box 28)
    - September 30, 1902-October 31, 1903 (Box 28)
    - November 2, 1903-May 17, 1904 (Box 28)
    - May 18, 1904-November 17, 1904 (Box 28)
    - November 16, 1904-August 7, 1905 (Box 29)
    - August 8, 1905-February 26, 1906 (Box 29)
    - February 26, 1906-July 26, 1907 (Box 29)
    - January 15, 1907-August 30, 1907 (Box 29)
    - August 30, 1907-March 18, 1908 (Box 30)
      (also some business correspondence, Feb.-June 1907)
    - March 18, 1908-September 16, 1908 (Box 30)
    - September 17, 1908-March 31, 1909 (Box 30)
    - April 1, 1909-September 20, 1909 (Box 30)
    - April 1, 1909-September 20, 1909 (Box 30)
    - September 20, 1909-March 10, 1910 (Box 30)
    - March 14, 1910-July 14, 1910 (Box 31)
    - July 14, 1910-November 28, 1910 (Box 31)
    - November 28, 1910-March 24, 1911 (Box 31)
    - March 25, 1911-September 18, 1911 (Box 31)
    - September 19, 1911-March 1912 (Box 31)
    - March 23, 1912-August 8, 1912-December 24, 1912 (Box 32)
    - December 24, 1912-April 30, 1913 (Box 32)
    - May 2, 1913-October 29, 1913 (Box 32)
    - October 28, 1913-February 19, 1914 (Box 33)
    - February 19, 1914-June 15, 1914 (Box 33)
    - June 16, 1914-November 5, 1914 (Box 33)
    - November 5, 1914-February 18, 1915 (Box 33)
    - February 19, 1915-August 26, 1915 (Box 34)
    - August 26, 1915-December 30, 1915 (Box 34)
    - December 31, 1915-April 25, 1916 (Box 34)
    - April 25, 1916-November 10, 1916 (Box 34)
    - November 11, 1916-April 28, 1917 (Box 35)
    - April 27, 1917-October 26, 1917 (Box 35)
    - October 27, 1917-April 3, 1918 (Box 35)
    - April 4, 1918-November 1, 1918 (Box 35)
    - November 1, 1918-April 1, 1919 (Box 36)
    - April 1, 1919-August 7, 1919 (Box 36)
    - August 8, 1919-December 1, 1919 (Box 36)
    - December 1, 1919-April 27, 1920 (Box 36)
    - April 27, 1920-December 17, 1920 (Box 36)
    - December 17, 1920-May 13, 1921 (Box 37)
    - May 20, 1921-December 7, 1921 (Box 37)
    - December 7, 1921-July 10, 1922 (Box 37)
    - July 11, 1922-June 18, 1923 (Box 37)
    - January 19, 1923-July 23, 1923 (Box 37)
    - July 24, 1923-February 15, 1924 (Box 38)
    - February 15, 1924-September 22, 1924 (Box 38)
    - September 23, 1924-May 11, 1925 (Box 38)
    - May 15, 1925-February 18, 1926 (Box 38)
    - February 18, 1926-November 22, 1926 (Box 39)
    - November 23, 1926-September 20, 1927 (Box 39)
    - September 20, 1927-September 29, 1928 (Box 39)
    - October 3, 1928-September 9, 1929 (Box 39)
    - September 9, 1929-September 26, 1930 (Box 40)
    - September 27, 1930-July 28, 1931 (Box 40)
    - July 29, 1931-July 12, 1932 (Box 40)
    - July 12, 1932-September 20, 1933 (Box 40)
    - September 21, 1933-November 14, 1934 (Box 41)
    - November 19, 1934-May 12, 1936 (Box 41)
  - Saginaw and Manistee Lumber Company
    - Letterbook, October 29, 1917-August 26, 1919 (Box 41)
    - Letterbook, August 27, 1919-December 26, 1921 (Box 41)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 41)
  - Hunting and Fishing
    - Letterbook of Michigan Forestry Association, 1908-1913 (Box 42)
    - Record book of Michigan Wildlife Conservation Association and Michigan Sportmen's Association, 1919-1920 (Box 42)
    - Membership book: The Michigan Sportmen's Association (Box 42)
    - Saginaw Forest and Stream Club (Box 42)
    - Record book, 1917-1923 (Box 42)
    - Forest and Stream Co. Ltd. (Box 42)
    - Stock subscription book [includes minutes, 1894-1910; and history of Saginaw Hunting Club (founded 1883) 1894-1910 (Box 42)
    - Record book: Fishing Conditions on Au Sable River, 1909-1932 (Box 42)
    - Record book: Fishing Conditions on Au Sable River, 1933-1936 (Box 42)
    - Hunting and Travel memorandum books (Box 43)
    - Typescripts of hunting and travel memorandum books (Box 43)
    - Hunting and travel miscellanea (Box 43)
    - Chart relating to fish habits, 6 items (Folder Ac)
  - Business Papers
    - Correspondence concerning Lumberman's memorial, 1928-1932 (Box 44)
    - W.B. Mershon & Co.
      - Trial balance sheets, 1913-1925 (Box 44)
      - Minutes of board of directors and stockholders, 1918-1928 (Box 45)
        (include supplementary report for period, 1889-1917)
      - Record of stockholders and articles of association (Box 45)
      - Journal, 1899; 1928-1930; 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 45)
      - Record book, including "Black List" of employees, circa 1884-1899 (Box 45)
      - Price Lists (Box 45)
      - Record of securities: Catherine C. Mershon and William B. Mershon, 1923-1937 (Box 45)
    - Chicago, Kalamazoo and Saginaw Railroad Company Record book of bond signers, 1884 (Box 45)
    - Personal account books (Box 45)
    - Miscellanea (Box 45)
    - Clippings (Box 45)
    - Balance sheets, of the Calumet and Arizona Mining Company, 1922-1931 (Box 46)
    - Receipts for July 4th celebration, 1895, Saginaw, Mich., 1 items (Folder Ac)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs (Box 47)
      - Canada (Box 47)
      - Cascapedia River fishing trips, circa 1902-1913 (Box 47)
        [1]
      - General camping and river views, circa 1905-1930s (Box 47)
        [2]
      - Camping scenes (includes 1902 Black River trip) (Box 47)
        [3]
      - Family, friends, pets (Box 47)
        [4]
      - Fish and fish habits (including breeding areas) (Box 47)
        [5]
      - Fish and fish habits (drawings) (Box 47)
        [6]
      - Fishing scenes, 1887; 1930s (Box 47)
        [7]
      - Forest views (Box 47)
        (including David Ward estate and Pine Grove Camp)
        [8]
      - Hunting trips (Box 47)
        (also includes Africa and Scotland)
        [9]
      - Lumbering scenes (Rust Brothers camp and others on Tittabawassee River, 1890s) (Box 47)
        [10]
      - Miscellaneous (including western mining scenes, 1910) (Box 47)
        [12]
      - Portraits and snapshots (Box 47)
        [13]
      - Recollections of My Fifty Years Hunting and Fishing (photos used in book) (Box 47)
        [14]
      - Saginaw, Mich.
        - Bliss Park development, 1906-1908 (Box 47)
          [15]
        - Rochester Salt and Lumber Co., 1880s (Box 47)
      - Travels (American southwest and Europe) (Box 47)
        [16]
    - Albums
      - Pinacote (Mexico, Arizona and California trip), 1915 (Box 47)
      - Picnic at Ajo, Arizona, 1920 (Box 47)
        Includes Papago Indians and architecture.
      - Tawas Beach and other snapshots of family, 1903-1905 (Box 47)
      - Family and camping snapshots., 1907-1919 (Box 47)
        Locations: Bridgeport, Pasadena, the Mackinaw ferry, Buffalo Lake, Coleman Lake (Arizona), Mississippi, Cascapedia (Gaspe), Lovells, Black River, Au Sable River, High Bank Lodge and the "portable house."
      - Hunting, family and travel album., 1907-1911 (Box 47)
        Includes railroad hunting car, lodge at Buffalo Lake, the portable house and Saskatchewan.
      - Large album, with fishing, travel and vacation photos in Newfoundland, Quebec, New Brunswick, New Hampshire, France and California. Includes Merson fishing lodge on Casapedia River in Quebec., 1899-1905 (Box 47)
      - Large album with family and hunting photos, circa 1910 (Box 47)
- Microfilmed records
  - William B. Mershon & Company
    - Ledgers (Reel 1)
      - 1887-1888 (Reel 1)
      - 1889 (Reel 1)
      - 1890 (Reel 1)
      - 1891-1892 (Reel 1)
        (cont. on reel 2)
      - 1891-1892 (Reel 2)
        (cont. from reel 1)
      - 1893-1895 (Reel 2)
      - 1896-1898 (Reel 2)
      - 1899-1902 (Reel 3)
      - 1903-1906 (Reel 3)
      - 1907-1914 (Reel 3)
      - 1907-1920 (Reel 4)
      - 1925-1926 (Reel 4)
    - Individual (Sales) Ledgers (Reel 5)
      - 1891-1892 (Reel 5)
      - 1893-1895 (Reel 5)
      - 1896-1898 (Reel 5)
      - 1899-1902 (Reel 6)
      - 1903-1906 (Reel 6)
      - 1907-1913 (Reel 6)
        [A-R]
      - 1907-1912 (Reel 7)
        [R-Z]
      - 1907-1920 (Reel 7)
        [M-Z]
      - 1921-1926 (Reel 7)
        [A-L]
      - 1921-1926 (Reel 8)
    - Journals
      - 1883-1886 (Reel 8)
      - 1886-1888 (Reel 8)
      - 1889-1890 (Reel 8)
      - 1891-1892 (Reel 9)
      - 1892-1895 (Reel 9)
      - 1896-1899 (Reel 9)
        (cont. on reel 10)
      - 1896-1899 (Reel 10)
        (cont. from reel 9)
      - 1900-1906 (Reel 10)
      - 1907-1910 (Reel 10)
      - 1911-1915 (Reel 11)
      - November 1915-1920 (Reel 11)
      - November 1920-1925 (Reel 11)
      - May 1925-1928 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous Journals (Box 11)
      - 1888-1889 (Box 11)
    - Payroll
      - 1909-1913 (Reel 12)
      - 1914-1918 (Reel 12)
      - 1919-1923 (Reel 12)
      - 1924-1946 (Reel 12)
      - June 1912-April 1913 (Reel 12)
    - Stockholders and Directors Meetings, 1889-1918 (Reel 12)
    - Production records, 1903-1915 (Reel 12)
  - Mershon, Schuette and Parker
    - Order books
      - 1903-1904 (Reel 13)
      - 1904-1905 (Reel 13)
      - 1906-1908 (Reel 13)
      - 1908-1912 (Reel 13)
  - Atlas Oil Corporation
    - Records, 1926-1929 (Reel 13)
  - Hanson, Mershon and Morley Company
    - Tree survey and other information (Reel 13)
  - Saginaw and Manistee Lumber Co.
    - Stockholders and Director's meetings, 1899-1925 (Reel 13)
  - Personal Journals
    - 1903-February 1907 (Reel 13)
    - March 1907-1910 (Reel 13)
    - 1911-1915 (Reel 13)
    - 1916-1920 (Reel 14)
    - 1921-1927 (Reel 14)
    - 1928-1937 (Reel 14)
    - 1938-1943 (Reel 14)